Okay, so but so again starting you know where we are on
כח עמוד ב Kaf Chet Amud Bet the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא
Gemara says that you do everything in the סוכה Sukkah for the
seven days or you make the סוכה Sukkah fixed, which is you
put all your nice stuff there. It's how you set up the
environment of the סוכה, Sukkah, your nice mattresses, and what you do
in the סוכה. Sukkah. So just hanging out in the סוכה. Sukkah.
Yeah, not that that's strictly obligated, you're allowed to do it outside
of the סוכה, Sukkah, but that this is how you do the
מצוה Mitzvah in its best possible form. And the same eating and
drinking, echoing back to the discussion before, you know about the people
that said מעלם לסוכה, Ma'alam LaSukkah, let's bring it up to the
סוכה Sukkah because it's nice, ideal to be doing everything in the
סוכה. Sukkah. מנא הני מילי, Minani Milei, where is this from? דתנו
רבנן, Detanu Rabbanan, so this next ברייתא Braita is going to be
pretty similar to the first ברייתא, Braita, except it links it to
a verse. תשבו, Teshvu, you shall dwell seven days in the סוכות.
Sukkot. So this is the classic sort of phrase we've been doing.
כעין תדורו Ke'ein Taduru means dwell in the סוכה Sukkah like you
dwell in your house. מכאן אמרו, Mikan Amru, from here they said,
כל שבעת ימים עושה אדם סוכתו קבע וביתו עראי, Kol Shiv'at Yamim
Oseh Adam Sukkato Keva UVeito Arai, you make your סוכה Sukkah your
fixed and your house temporary. כיצד, Keitzad, how does that translate? היו
לו כלים נאים מעלם לסוכה, Hayu Lo Kelim Na'im Ma'alam LaSukkah, you
have nice vessels, various types of things,
bring it up to the סוכה. Sukkah. מצעות נאים מעלם לסוכה, Matzo'ot
Na'im Ma'alam LaSukkah, you have nice bedding, you bring it into the
סוכה. Sukkah. אוכל ושותה ומטייל בסוכה, Ochel Veshotte Umtiyel BaSukkah, you just
spend time, you eat and you drink in the סוכה. Sukkah. And
adding something we didn't have before, ומשנה בסוכה, Umeshaneh BaSukkah, you do
your learning in a סוכה. Sukkah. You try to be in the
סוכה Sukkah as much as and you create an environment as similar
to that as you would want in your home. Okay, so now
the גמרא's Gemara going to look at the issue about learning. איני,
Inei, is that really true that you learn in the סוכה? Sukkah?
והאמר רבא, VeHa'amar Rava, because ומשנה Umeshaneh specifically indicates the type of
an analytical learning, the תלמודי Talmudic type of a learning that a
person would do. But doesn't רבא Rava say, מקרא ומשנה במטללתא, Mikra
UMishna BiMtalulta, when he when you're learning מקרא, Mikra, פסוקים, Psukim, תנ"ך,
Tanakh, or משנה Mishna when you're just going over the received sort
of traditions and you know what we would call the the משנה,
Mishna, that is in the סוכה Sukkah because that's not that doesn't
require like an enormous amount of a focus you know or of
of intensive sort of you know intellectual application, that's mostly memorization. ותנויי,
VeTanuyei, but the analytical aspect of it, what we would call the
גמרא, Gemara, בר ממטללתא, Bar MiMtalulta, you do that outside the סוכה.
Sukkah. You go to a better environment to be doing it, maybe
outside where the air is better, maybe you go to the בית
מדרש, Beit Midrash, that you don't have to do in the סוכה.
Sukkah. So so how does that fit with what we said? So
the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, Lo Kashya, הא במיגרס הא בעיוני.
Ha BeMigras Ha BeIyunyei. Even when it comes to sort of גמרא,
Gemara, there are two aspects of it. There's one is the memorization
of it and the other is the doing the analytical work. What
does that mean? What does it mean to memorize גמרא? Gemara? I
mean the whole point of גמרא Gemara is analysis. But as we
know, after other people have done the analysis, then the גמרא Gemara
itself becomes a text to be learned. So the גמרא Gemara says,
כי הא דרבא, Ki Ha DeRava, like רבא, Rava, רב פפא, Rav
Papa, כי הוה קמיה דרב חסדא, Ki Hava Kamei DeRav Chisda, when
he was in the presence of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
מרצי בגמרא בהדי הדדי. Meratzi BeGemara Bahadi Hadadei. So no, it's not
excuse me, it's רבא ורמי Rava VeRami because there are two people.
If you look at the side, כי הא דרבא ורמי בר חמא.
Ki Ha DeRava VeRami Bar Chama. So רבא Rava and רמי בר
חמא, Rami Bar Chama, when they were in the plural in front
of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, they would like מרצי Meratzi means really
to run through. So they'd run through the גמרא Gemara with one
another, meaning they'd be sitting in front of another בחברותא be-chavruta and
maybe רב חסדא Rav Chisda would tell them over the analysis and
discussion and they would review it amongst themselves and they'd memorize it
and that they that would be stage one, memorize what was taught
even in terms of the גמרא Gemara that was taught, the analysis
that was taught. והדר, VeHadar, and then after they had it down
clear, מעייני בסברא, Ma'aynei BiSvara,
then they would apply their analytical ability and they would start thinking
about it. But what did he mean when he said this and
what about that and what about that? And then they'd start sort
of thinking on their own after they had down the text and
the tradition that they were receiving. So when it comes, when the
גמרא Gemara is sort of like מקרא Mikra and משנה, Mishna, when
it's about just memorizing what's being said, not actually analyzing it, that
you can do in the סוכה Sukkah even though the conditions might
not be ideal. But when you come to do the analysis, that
already you're going to do outside of the סוכה Sukkah where you're
going to have better ideal conditions. Now it doesn't have to exactly
be framed as like תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah trumps סוכה, Sukkah, like
they're competing, so when it's going to come at the expense of
תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is going to win
out. You know it could just be understood like everything else we've
been doing until now, which is is that you know you don't
have to do your סוכה Sukkah isn't a prison. You don't have
to do everything in a סוכה. Sukkah. So the types of things
that you normally would not do in your house, you know you're
not required to do in a סוכה. Sukkah. So if in your
house it's not always most you know conducive to doing a certain
type of learning and you'd go to the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash,
you'd go outdoors or you'd go where it's more quiet or whatever,
then the same reality applies in the סוכה. Sukkah. The same way
like if you're מצטער Mitztayer or you have other types of things,
you know. The ability to learn the way you need to learn
is also one of them. Okay, but that's again, all what's interesting
here is we're not just talking about the narrow very concrete quantified
obligation of sleeping or eating an אכילת קבע. achilas keva. You know,
even there we talked about exemptions in terms of about שומר עיר
shomer iro and מהלכי דרכים, mahalchei drachim, but here we're talking about
even the ideal, the ideal is not to be defined in just
narrow quantitative terms. The fullest sense of like the bare minimum that
we could say you were יושב בסוכה yoshev basukkah is you slept
and you ate X amount in a סוכה. sukkah. But what it
really means to be יושב בסוכה yoshev basukkah is to do everything
described here and to do it in the fullest. But even doing
it in the fullest, your סוכה sukkah doesn't become a prison, right?
So even if you're trying to do everything, doesn't literally mean everything,
means everything that would be a natural part of what it means
to live in a place. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now that
we're talking about not only what you do, what activities you do,
but how you set up the סוכה, sukkah, we're gonna continue with
that as well. אמר רבא Amar Rava says Rava, מאני דמשתיא, manei
d'mishtaya, drinking glasses, במטללתא, b'matalalta, that even after you're done drinking, you
can leave them in the סוכה. sukkah. That's because they don't get
like dirty and disgusting. מאני דמיכלא, manei d'michla, but the dishes, vessels
for eating, בר ממטללתא, bar m'matalalta, after you finish eating it, he
didn't say after but that seems to be the context, you have
to take it out of the סוכה sukkah because it's not respectful
of the סוכה. sukkah. And also the same way, you know, if
you're gonna hang around after the dinner table after the meal's over
to be שמוזינג schmoozing and spending time, you want to be clearing
the table. You don't want all the chicken bones and all the
greasy plates on the table. So if you want to create the
right environment, meaning you could just say like it's not respectful to
the מצוה. mitzvah. But even forgetting talking about the מצוה, mitzvah, if
you want to be spending time in the סוכה sukkah and making
it an environment that's conducive to spending time and that's like your
home, then you don't want to be taking these disgusting stuff out
of the סוכה, sukkah, so you'll want to be more in the
סוכה. sukkah. Okay, so you take- you clear the dishes off the
table, make sure to remove them from the
סוכה. sukkah. חצבא ושכייא chatzba v'shichaya בר ממטללתא, bar m'matalalta, if you
have like a pottery pitcher or a wooden bucket, you know, so
after you obviously pour the water from them that you need them,
again, take it out of the סוכה. sukkah. Have the סוכה sukkah
remain
a very welcoming, pleasant environment.
ושרגא, v'sharga, but the candle, במטללתא b'matalalta should be in the סוכה.
sukkah. Maybe not only are you allowed to, but that if there's
light in the סוכה, sukkah, you'll stay in the סוכה. sukkah. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואמרי לה v'amri lah בר ממטללתא, bar m'matalalta,
but some say you keep the candle out of סוכה. sukkah. So
לא פליגי, lo pligi, they don't debate, הא בסוכה גדולה הא בסוכה
קטנה. ha b'sukkah gedolah ha b'sukkah ketanah. If it's a big סוכה
sukkah you have the candle in it. If it's a small סוכה,
sukkah, this is while the candle's lit as opposed to the other
discussions is when you were done eating with it and done using
it, but if the candle is lit, you don't want it in
a small סוכה sukkah because you're gonna be afraid the סוכה sukkah
is gonna burn down and you're not gonna want to stay in
the סוכה, sukkah, so you have to have it out. But again,
it really would be interesting to think what would it mean to
be doing this in a serious way, right? Besides that we've already
talked about just the basic obligation of sleeping in the סוכה sukkah
which we tend not to do, but trying really to spend your,
you know, your time, the amount of time you'd spend in your
house to spend it in a סוכה. sukkah. You know, if you
wanted to be reading a novel, you go read a novel in
a סוכה, sukkah, you want- you go take out your computer, your
TV, you know, you go whatever if it's a little bit too
hot so you bring out a portable air conditioner into the סוכה,
sukkah, you know, you run- you run electric lights. I mean, people
anyway tend, you know, run electric lights just so they can eat
there at night. But what would it really mean to go to
the effort to set up the סוכה sukkah so it would be
so conducive that, you know, again, assuming that you're not have to
be dealing with things you can't control, like the mosquitoes or overly
humid or rain or whatever, but it would be so conducive assuming
nice weather that you'd actually just want to be hanging out in
the סוכה. sukkah. You know, so it would be possible to make
it a lot more welcoming than we do, and what this is
reflecting, it's not just your choice, "I'm gonna spend time," it's what
are you doing to create the environment that helps make that possible.
Yes, Charlie.
Are they gonna define large versus small סוכה? sukkah?
No. I mean large, presumably large enough that you don't have to
worry about the סכך schach catching on fire and you're not concerned
about those things. Okay. Yeah, so just- just the
existence of these things, so the things that we spend time with
inside the סוכה, sukkah, things like whether you bring
in any, you know, start reading the newspapers and everything, right? Are
you somehow maybe- Yeah, so you know, right, I mean look, well
okay, I mean I would say things you shouldn't be watching on
television indoors you shouldn't be watching in- and it's an interesting question,
like there's a famous משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah where he talks about
spending time in a סוכה sukkah but then talking לשון הרע lashon
hara in the סוכה sukkah because what do you do if you're
hanging around too much? So you start gossiping. So, you know, you
shouldn't be talking לשון הרע lashon hara anywhere, but is it worse
to be- worse to be talking לשון הרע lashon hara in the
סוכה? sukkah? You know, so it's interesting because and we're actually gonna
get to this in a minute, the whole thing we've been talking
about about this theme that the סוכה's sukkah like under the ענני
כבוד ananei hakavod and in
the- the divine... well I'd say two things. First of all, being
more of a halakhist than a sort of kabbalist or somebody who
goes just more concrete הלכה, Halakha, I would say don't let those
ideas compromise the sort of more halakhic demand here or the ideal
nature of the מצוה. Mitzvah. And since the ideal nature of the
מצוה Mitzvah is to spend time, so sure, read a newspaper, read
your novel, I mean as long as again we're talking about
activity that's acceptable, even if it's not מצוה Mitzvah related, even if
it's not holy activity. I mean you sleep in the סוכה, Sukkah,
eat in the
סוכה, Sukkah, right? I mean here's an interesting question, not to be
scandalous or anything. A woman is exempt from the סוכה, Sukkah, but
if a husband and wife choose to both be in the סוכה
Sukkah and sleep in the סוכה, Sukkah, can they have sex in
the סוכה, Sukkah, right? How much is it supposed to really be
your home? And one of the powers of the idea of the
ענני הכבוד Ananei HaKavod is, and this is interesting again, a lot
of what I'm sharing by the way, and I think I said
this before but I need to say it again, is not just
my own thought but this wonderful book which was based on his
doctoral dissertation by a Rabbi Yaakov Nagen, originally name is Yaakov Genack,
son of Menachem Genack from the OU. Rabbi Yaakov Nagen who is
a ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva or ר''מ Ram in ישיבת עתניאל Yeshivat
Otniel wrote his PhD on some of the major sort of religious
themes in מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah and how it intersects with some
of the other sort of halakhic discussions. And one of the major
ones was about this issue about סוכה, Sukkah, ענני הכבוד, Ananei HaKavod,
and a sense of the divine presence over the סוכה Sukkah like
we again talked about the model of the משכן Mishkan and of
the
שבעת ימי המילואים Shivas Yemei HaMiluim when Aaron and his children dwelt
in the משכן Mishkan and the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, but also
what he points out is that one of the power real powers
of that is when you bring together the two images: the image
of סוכה Sukkah as your house and the image of ענני הכבוד
Ananei HaKavod and God's presence. And then sort of the message is
bringing the fullest divine presence totally within the home, like bringing those
two realities together. It's not just like you go to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash for God's presence and you go to your home
and those are sort of separate realities. But what does it mean
to try to merge those two realities? So in a way, I
think that you could in a very powerful way say that it's
not even compromising the idea of the סוכה Sukkah the holy place.
The whole idea is to make that same סוכה Sukkah which is
your home also the place of the divine presence and the ענני
הכבוד Ananei HaKavod and to sort of bring those two together. But
I would definitely say that yes, look, ideally what should you be
doing with your extra time? Fine, you should be learning your תורה
Torah the whole time. But if you're anyway gonna be, you're gonna
be reading the newspaper and reading a novel, go ahead and read
it in the סוכה, Sukkah, make the סוכה Sukkah your home and
that's actually the point here. Yeah, so the סכך Schach has some
הלכות Halakhot of אהל Ohel and טומאה Tumah
apply inside the סוכה. Sukkah. The סכך Schach is חוצץ? Chotzetz? It
doesn't חוצץ? Chotzetz? If I have it inside your
house during the rest of
the year, הקדוש ברוך
הוא
Hakadosh
Baruch
Hu and the שכינה Shekhinah is
not like hovering over because it's not סכך. Schach.
סכך Schach enables that proximity? No,
you can't say that. That a normal roof is certainly חוצץ בפני
הטומאה Chotzetz Bifnei HaTumah the same way the סכך Schach is. Yeah,
you can't, so that's an interesting creative approach to see if you
can sort of make the halakhic aspects reinforce that, but I'm not,
I'm not sure you can get go get that far, but you
can try it. All right, so now let's get back to the
גמרא. Gemara. ירדו
גשמים, Yardu Geshamim, so rain comes down. So the גמרא Gemara says
תנא, Tana, משתסרח המקפה, Mishetyisrach HaMikpah, what it means that as soon
as it starts getting spoiled that you can go in. So it
says the, when the porridge is spoiled, so גריסין Grisim of gru...
I think גריסין Grisim is grits? Is that how they translate גריסין?
Grisim?
Or was it barley? Is it bran, barley, something like that?
Split beans? What?
Split
beans? Okay? What? Split beans? Pounded grain? All right, fine. Anyway, when
that porridge spoils, which is a very easy to spoil... Now, presumably
this is based on the principle that מצטער, Mista'er, somebody that's sort
of discomforted is exempt from the סוכה, Sukkah, but you might remember
that the statement מצטער פטור מן הסוכה Mista'er Patur Min HaSukkah came
from רבא. Rava. And this is a משנה. Mishna. So what was
רבא's Rava חידוש Chiddush if the משנה Mishna is saying that you
go in once it starts raining and becomes uncomfortable? And the difference
might be that if rain is coming into the סוכה, Sukkah, it's
not just that you personally are מצטער Mista'er and therefore you're exempt,
it could be it stops being a סוכה, Sukkah, right? The סוכה
Sukkah starts, stops losing its identity as a domicile if you've got
a house with a leaky roof, that would be,
that's no longer a domicile. It might even be considered like a
condemned building.
The משנה Mishna doesn't use a לשון Lashon of צער.
Tza'ar. I know, that was my point. So if we try to
explain it, we might want to think about putting it into this
category that we've been taught until now called מצטער, Mista'er, but that's
not the לשון Lashon of the משנה Mishna and it might be
based more on whether it continues to be considered a סוכה. Sukkah.
Okay, אביי הוה יתיב קמיה דרב יוסף. Abaye Hava Kayasiv Kamei DeRav
Yosef. אביי Abaye was sitting... Abaye was sitting in the presence of
Rav
Yosef במטלתא. B'metaltah. Rav Yosef was his רבי rebbi in a סוכה.
sukkah. נשב זיקא, Nashav zika, the wind blew, וקמייתי ציבותא, vekamayti tzivuta,
and the little pine needles or whatever fell out of the סכך.
schach. אמר להו רב יוסף, Amar lehu Rav Yosef, and it was
falling into people's soup and in their face. So Rav Yosef said
to the people gathered around, פנו לי מאני מהכא, Pinu li mani
meihacha, remove my vessels from here, meaning I'm going, I'm going in,
bring in my all of my various, my clothes, my vessels, my
כלים, kelim, we're going back into the house. So אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, Abaye said to him, והתנן משתסרח המקפה, Vehatnan mishetitroach
hamerek, but we said only when the porridge spoils, it's a little
annoying, but it's not at that stage. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back
to him, לדידי כיון דאניני דעתי, Lididi kivan d'aninai da'ati, as far
as I'm concerned, since I am so fastidious, since I am so
sensitive to these things, כמשתסרח המקפה דמי, K'mishetitroach hamerek dami, it's as
bad as the porridge spoiling, which is a very important point, which
is it's not just measured by some objective standard that everybody would
be bothered by it, it's even true subjectively if it's not tolerable
by you. But this already, we're no longer talking about rain, we're
talking at a subjective level you can't tolerate, and we're talking about
things like the pine needles falling down, I think that's a very
American reality, pine needles, whatever, the, right, pine trees don't grow in
like the Middle East, do they? Anyway, whatever, the various things from
the סכך schach falling down, we're not talking about, it sounds like,
at least according to Rav Yosef and Abaye, they are interpreting it
more in this מצטער mitztaer type of a category, personal discomfort, and
therefore it could be more subjective and it wouldn't be limited to
things like the rain and so on.
לשון אנינות, Lashon aninut, אנינות aninut
is, אניני דעתא Aninei da'ata is לשון אנינות. lashon aninut.
Oh, that's a good point. I'm not exactly sure about the same
etymology. רש"י Rashi quotes a very famous גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim
that says three people's lives are not real lives because they're like
just
constantly sort of troubled, people that are overly compassionate so they're always
feeling other people's pains, people that get overly angry so they're always,
they're always upset, and people that are אניני דעת, Aninei da'at, people
that are
very fastidious and the slightest sort of change in the
environment could have is upsets them. And then Rav Yosef says I
have all three of those problems. So anyway, all right.
I have planted pine seedlings in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
In ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Okay, so I don't know if they're
native. I don't know if they're native or not. Anyway, fine. But
this is translating this a little bit more as מצטער. mitztaer. I
should mention by the way that it's an interesting question להלכה, l'halacha,
like we say, at what point if the סוכה sukkah allows for
these things to happen and regularly is given for or is not
generally habitable, then to what degree are you not יוצא yotze even
when you could live in it? Like for example, if you make
a סוכה sukkah that that is constantly gets mosquitoes or
mosquitoes are constantly there, so when the mosquitoes are there everybody can
leave because it's מצטער, mitztaer, but even when the mosquitoes aren't there
do you say like how could you call this place a house
if it regularly is, if mosquitoes are regularly invading it?
So and or here's another example, let's say it's
just a very cold
climate and you haven't made the סוכה, sukkah, you could put in
heaters, you didn't, but if you're so regularly מצטער, mitztaer, then how
could you actually ever be יוצא yotze in this סוכה sukkah if
it's not normally made for being fit to be habitable? So I
raise this because the question is why we don't sleep in a
סוכה, sukkah, and one of the reasons given is because the גמרא
Gemara is talking about ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, which is Mediterranean climate
where it's nice and warm and it's gorgeous on סוכות, Sukkot, but
then when people moved to, even before Poland, but certainly Poland, but
Germany and France and so on, it's so freezing you can't sleep
in a סוכה. sukkah. Fine. But if it's never possible to sleep
in it, so it's not a domicile that's ever fit for sleeping,
then how is it ever even considered a סוכה sukkah and how
are you יוצא yotze even eating in it? So it does raise
these interesting types of questions of can situationalities undermine its identity as
סוכה? sukkah? Like if it rains, are we just saying that that
means that you're personally מצטער, mitztaer, or do we say no, if
it's raining it stops being a סוכה? sukkah? And if we say
that then can we talk about a more
general sort of view that if it allows for certain types of
realities, even if it provides סכך, schach, can you really consider it
to be a domicile? We tend to
be not, not to make problems with that, we tend to say
yeah, even if it's going to be too cold to sleep in
and even if there are often mosquitoes that are going to get
in, but when those aren't problems we're still going to call it
a סוכה, sukkah, and translate these issues less about the identity of
the סוכה sukkah and more only about if I personally מצטער. mitztaer.
can't tolerate it, and that's also what the גמרא Gemara did with
the case of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. It sort of used the
example of raining in a סוכה sukkah to be a more individual
focus of am I מצטער mitzta'er or not מצטער. mitzta'er. Yes, Charlie?
Oh, excuse me, first of all, in pine tree native to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Oh, perfect, so it could be talking about pine leaves, yes.
And then also to mention, second,
the when Jews went to northern Europe in the early middle ages,
the climate was significantly warmer than it is today. Very. And I
was wondering when did the issue of don't bother sleeping in a
סוכה sukkah start to be discussed?
Right. I mean, the רמ"א Rama certainly says that our מנהג minhag
is not to sleep in a סוכה. sukkah.
That was about when things got colder.
Interesting. I'd have to find out what the earliest mentions of that
are.
I think to the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah if I remember correctly
talks about how much snow needs to be in the סוכה sukkah
before you can leave.
Could be, could be. Okay. Yes.
In ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, this is a transition from the dry
season to the rainy season. So perhaps looking at rain in terms
of a meaning to it might have something to do with that,
whereas up here we expect this kind of rain.
Right, that's a very good point. And the rain, and that's an
excellent point, and that actually is a wonderful transition to the next
part of the משנה, Mishnah, which we'll get to in a second.
You know, particularly it's the time you start saying משיב הרוח ומוריד
הגשם. mashiv haruach umorid hagashem. And as you say, if you're transitioning
to the rainy season and you need the rain to see more
generally the sort of theological significance of rain, particularly during this time,
even if that theological significance is going to be interpreted negatively, but
nevertheless, given those realities, to give it that weight. Thank you, that's
a very important insight. But obviously it becomes a time that you
need rain and it has all of that deeper meaning. Okay. So
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, one more statement, very important about some of
the הלכות halachot about going in, about when you have to be
in a סוכה, sukkah, this is very relevant. היה אוכל בסוכה וירדו
גשמים, Haya ochel basukkah veyardu geshamim, you're eating in a סוכה sukkah
and it starts raining, וירד, veyarad, and then you went down. It
says went down because the assumption is, right, remember the line beforehand,
העלום לסוכה, he'alum lasukkah, bring it up to the סוכה, sukkah, because
the סוכה sukkah was on the rooftop. So you went down, and
then it stops raining. אין מטריחין אותו לעלות עד שיגמור סעודתו, Ein
matrikhin oto la'alot ad sheyigmor se'udato, you don't have to go back
up and you know, in the middle of the meal and continue
eating. Once you were allowed to leave the סוכה, sukkah, then you
can finish eating the meal. What exactly that's based on, is it
based on an idea of מצטער? mitzta'er? It would now be a
צער tza'ar for you to interrupt the meal. Is it based on
a type of תשבו כעין תדורו teshvu k'ein taduru that if you,
you know, you don't switch houses in the middle of a meal,
so since you were here, you're allowed to remain here. But that's
the הלכה. halacha.
What about ברכת המזון? Birkat Hamazon? Do you have to go back
up to?
Right, I mean, especially if you're continuing your meal here. היה ישן
תחת הסוכה, Haya yashen tachat hasukkah, you were sleeping under the
סוכה, sukkah, וירדו גשמים. veyardu geshamim. It's again, interesting, תחת הסוכה tachat
hasukkah means תחת הסכך, tachat haskhach, but we would expect it to
say היה ישן בסוכה. haya yashen basukkah. Anyway, you're sleeping in a
סוכה sukkah and the rain comes down, וירד, veyarad, and you went
and you went down into your home. אין מטריחין אותו לעלות, Ein
matrikhin oto la'alot, then it stops raining. You don't have to go
back into the סוכה sukkah in the middle of your sleep and
you know, wake up and go back into the סוכה, sukkah, עד
שיעור ad sheye'or until it... now, the spelling is an ע ayin
means until it becomes light. Because the גמרא Gemara said, איבעיא להו,
iba'ya lehu, we want to know what that last word was. עד
שיעור ad sheye'or with an ע ayin until you wake up, או
עד שיאור o ad sheye'or or with an א, aleph, when it
becomes light? That if it's daybreak, somebody needs to wake you and
get you into the סוכה, sukkah, even if you haven't woken up,
because maybe now it's considered like a new period, like that exemption
lasted during nighttime. It'd be funny why daybreak should make it different
since you're obligated, you know, to sleep there at night. Anyway, תא
שמע, ta shema, come and
hear. עד שיעור ויעלה עמוד השחר. ad sheye'or veya'aleh amud hashachar. We
have a ברייתא braita that says until it's יאור ye'or and the
morning star comes up. תרתי? Tarti? How could you say both? First
of all, if it means when it becomes light, then either they
mean the same thing, or as רש"י Rashi said, actually יאור ye'or
is a time that would be later than עמוד השחר. amud hashachar.
עמוד השחר Amud hashachar is like the morning star, a little light,
יאור ye'or means like everything has become light. So obviously they can't
be talking about both about the issue of time. אלא אימא, Ela
eima, עד שיעור ad sheye'or until you wake up ויעלה עמוד השחר
veya'aleh amud hashachar and the morning star comes up, meaning that you
need both. If you woke up and it's the middle of the
night, it's midnight and you happen to wake up, you don't have
to now transfer to the סוכה. sukkah. On the other hand, if
it's the morning and you're asleep, nobody has to wake you. Only
once you wake up and it's morning and meaning now is really
the time to get up and move around, then that's then you
have to then you know, that's now you have to get back
into the סוכה. sukkah. But again, like the סעודה, se'udah, fascinating idea
that even though now it's possible, you can continue outside. Is it
either an issue of מצטער mitzta'er or is it just more likely
of like a תשבו כעין תדורו? teshvu k'ein taduru? Once you're able,
you know, if I went over to my friend's house to sleep
over, you know, because there was some construction going on in my
house. Right? And then the guy called me as I was and
said,
"Oh, we're just done with the construction, we're moving out." Would I
actually go in the middle of the night and go back there?
Most probably not, I'd do it the next morning. If it stopped,
it was raining in one room and I switched to eat in
another room and somehow they fixed it, I wouldn't move back in
the middle of the meal, I'd finish my meal where I was.
So it's probably a similar idea of a type of a תשבו
כעין תדורו. teshvu k'ein taduru.
It's a real textual clarification.
Yeah, the ע' Ayin or the א'. Aleph. Right. Now we get
to the significance of the rain and this important point that was
made about its theological significance. משל למה הדבר דומה. Mashal l'mah hadavar
domeh. What is it like? Somebody comes to serve, to pour for
the master,
and the pitcher of water is spilled on his face. So איבעיא
להו, Ibay'u lehu, they ask the question מי שפך למי, Mi shafach
l'mi, who's spilling the water on whom? Meaning it could be that
it's like you're coming to pour for your master and you trip
and your pitcher falls the water spills on your master's face. So
that the idea would be you're coming to do a מצוה mitzvah
and
somehow you're making a mess of it and God isn't happy with
it. So it sort of signifies that you've made a mess of
things. Or is the symbolism, either way symbolism is God is not
happy, but or is the symbolism which more fits of course the
idea of water and water being spilled on someone that you're coming
to do the מצוה mitzvah and you're not necessarily making a mess
of the מצוה, mitzvah, maybe God is angry at you for other
reasons, but God is taking the pitcher of water and throwing the
water on your face and that's what's happening. You try to do
the מצוה, mitzvah, he throws the water on your face says get
out of here I don't want you I don't want your מצוה.
mitzvah. So תא שמע Ta shema come and hear דתניא detanya שפך
לו רבו קיתון על פניו. shafach lo rabbo kiton al panav. It's
like the master to make it explicit takes this water that you're
coming to give him or mix it with the wine and he's
displeased with you and throws it at your face ואמר לו אי
אפשי בשמושך, v'amar lo ee efshi b'shimushecha, I have no interest in
your service. So it's a real sense of rejection. It's very powerful.
I mean normally why would we interpret things in such this powerful
theological way? We wouldn't say that if somebody has a hard time
finding a לולב lulav it's like God is although we do tend
to say it a little bit by שופר shofar right? We say
like sometimes if the בעל תוקע ba'al tokeiah has a hard time
blowing it, it's like the שטן satan is coming and creating problems.
סרו כי כלי ציבור
מגמגם. Soro ki klei tzibur megamgem.
Right. So I think that we do say it, I think could
be two things. A, I think it could be the point that
was made which was excellent point about how in general rain during
this
time is read in very theological ways. But it also could be
the examples we just put out there שופר shofar and תפילה tefillah
and so on. Those מצוות mitzvot that are more done sort of
in directly as connecting with
God. Type of a תפילה, tefillah, type of a direct connection, there
maybe we're
more inclined to think about them as in theological ways. Like if
I'm eating מצה matzah and something it's a little stale or whatever
happens we don't necessarily give it. But if I'm coming to like
connect to God, blow
שופר, shofar, דאוון, davven, and something is a problem maybe we interpret
it more theologically and it gets back to the theme of the
degree that we see סוכה sukkah in the ענני כבוד ananei kavod
type of a way and directly under God's presence. So the idea
of coming to the presence of the
master and you're in the master's presence and the master is pushing
you out of his presence. Well look at that. If you're being
pushed out of the סוכה, sukkah, that's being compared to being pushed
out of the master's presence. Get out of my place. Right. So
again the implicit suggestion here that the סוכה sukkah is like in
God's presence hovering over the סוכה sukkah and being read in this
heavy theological way is very powerful. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
that it's talking about sort of interpreting certain things in theological ways
has a broader discussion not having to do with מצוות mitzvot but
having to do with more rarer occurrences than just the issue of
rain. And you'll understand why it's more likely to have understood these
theologically. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught. בזמן שהחמה לוקה, Bizman
shehachamah lokah, when the sun is smitten, probably means an eclipse a
partial or fuller or full eclipse. סימן רע לכל העולם, Siman ra
l'chol ha'olam, it's a bad sign for the entire world because the
sun is something that the whole world needs and it has this
universal sense. So כולו, kulo, the entire world. משל למה הדבר דומה,
Mashal l'mah hadavar domeh, what is it like? למלך בשר ודם, L'melech
basar vadam, a human king שעשה סעודה לעבדיו, she'asah seudah l'avadav, made
a feast for his servants. והניח פנס לפניהם, v'heniach panas lifneihem, and
he put a lantern in their presence. כעס עליהם, Ka'as aleihem, and
when
he got angry ואמר לעבדו, v'amar l'avdo, and he said to his
servant טול פנס מפניהם, tol panas mipneihem, take the lantern from away
והושיבם בחושך, v'hoshibam bachoshech, let them dwell in the darkness. The מהרש"א
Maharsha connects this to the famous מדרש midrash that God created the
world and then he created the human being and it's like he
said to the human being here I've laid out a banquet before
you the creation of the world and thinking about that the luminary...
and the sun and the moon and the stars in the פסוקים
pesukim in בראשית Bereishit say that והיו לאותות, vehayu leotot, they should
be for signs. So certainly right by the ancients these things were
interpreted, you know, in these very profound, you know, like as auguries
and these, you know, and these, you know, with these sort of
profound significance. So there God laid out the feast, created the sun,
and then for some reason He says, "You know what? Sit in
the dark," and He takes away the sun, and therefore it's obviously
a bad sign for the whole world.
Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, a ברייתא, Beraita, רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi
Meir omer, כל זמן שהמאורות לוקים, kol zeman shehamaorot lokim, whenever the
מאורות—now maorot מאורות maorot here does not mean sun, the מאורות maorot
means the lesser luminaries, the moon and the stars, so let's say
the moon, I don't know what it mean, I guess a star
maybe would be like a comet or something, what it would mean
for a star to be לוקה. loke. Anyway, when the מאורות maorot
are afflicted, סימן רע לשונאיהם של ישראל, siman ra lesoneihem shel Yisrael,
it's a bad sign for the Jewish people, it's said euphemistically. Why?
Why not a bad sign for everyone?
מפני שמלומדים במכותיהם, mipnei shemelumadim bemakotaihem, because they are accustomed, they know
that they often are the ones that are persecuted, they get smitten.
משל
לסופר mashal lesofer שבא לבית הספר, sheba lebeit hasefer, it's like a
schoolteacher coming to the schoolhouse, ורצועה בידו, veretzua beyado, and he's got
the strap in his hand. This was when it was obviously, you
know, accepted to inflict corporal punishment by schoolteachers and by parents on
children. So the guy's coming and he's sort of whapping the ruler
in his hand. So מי דואג, mi doeg, who starts getting worried?
מי שרגיל ללקות בכל יום ויום, mi sheragil lilkot bechol yom vayom,
the kid who is always getting whipped every day, he's the one
that gets worried. So if there's trouble coming to the world, since,
you know, generally afflictions often befall the Jewish people, so if there's
going to be afflictions, we start getting worried because we know that
we're often the ones that have, you know, on to whom the
afflictions fall. It's a very sort of depressing type of perspective on
things. The מהרש"א Maharsha tries to give it a slightly more positive
valence. And the מהרש"א Maharsha says, you know, if you're coming to
discipline kids, if there's one kid that like, it's a lost cause,
he's never going to learn regardless, it's not going to do any
good, so you don't bother disciplining him. Why should you discipline him?
It's not going to do any good. You only discipline the people,
the kids who are actually going to, you know, have potential. So
that's the way he wants to read it. You know, if you
see these things as a type of a discipline where it wakes
us up and it makes us do תשובה teshuva or makes us
act better, whatever, so that'll be more effective for בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. That's the way he wants to read the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
It's not uncommon to have lunar eclipses on Purim, Pesach, and Sukkot.
Really? That's fascinating.
Okay.
Because they're always in the 15th, 14th, 15th of the month.
Right. Very interesting. Okay, but although this we're not situating within the
חגים, chaggim, but that's fascinating. Look, the other question is why it's
being read this way since, you know, חז"ל Chazal were very, I
mean, you know, they did קידוש החודש, Kiddush Hachodesh, they were very
aware of astronomical realities, you know, and you would think
they would have known
it and they, right, they would have noticed a regularity about these
types of things. So I don't really know the answer to that.
Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. בזמן שהחמה לוקה, bizman
shehachama loka, סימן רע לעובדי כוכבים, siman ra leovdei kochavim, when the
sun is, you know,
is smitten, then it is a bad sign for the idolaters, because,
you know, the idolaters are compared more to the sun. It's, you
know, it's always, it's very strong. They tend to have it very
good in these days. You know, their fortunes don't wax and wane
like the moon does. לבנה לוקה, levana loka, when the moon is,
has an eclipse or otherwise is somehow smitten, סימן רע לשונאיהם של
ישראל, siman ra lesoneihem shel Yisrael, that's a bad sign for the
Jewish people. מפני שישראל מונים ללבנה, mipnei sheYisrael monim lalevana, because we
make our months and our calendars by the moon, ועובדי כוכבים לחמה,
veovdei kochavim lachama, and they do it by the sun. Okay. לקה
במזרח, laka bamizrach, if these things happened when the sun or the
moon was in the east, then סימן רע ליושבי מזרח, siman ra
leyoshvei mizrach, then maybe we'll make it a little bit more local.
It's only for those that dwell in the east. במערב, bamaarav, if
it happened when the luminaries were in the west, סימן רע ליושבי
מערב, siman ra leyoshvei maarav, it's only bad for people in the
west. באמצע הרקיע, beemtza harakia, if it happened when they're in the
middle of the sky, סימן רע לכל העולם כולו, siman ra lechol
haolam kulo, it's bad for everyone. כולו. kulo. פניו דומים לדם, panav
domim ledam, now if the face of again the moon or the
sun is like red, sometimes there is this like reddish tinge around
these eclipses, so חרב בא לעולם, cherev ba laolam, so that's like
blood. That means that what's going to happen is that there'll be
war. לשק, lesak, if it's like a grayer, like a sackcloth, חצי
רעב באין לעולם, chizei raav ba-in laolam, that means a time of
famine. Why? רש"י Rashi says because a sack is more black and
your face has turned black. The מהרש"א Maharsha says because sack suggests
what's in the sack, which is the wheat. I assumed it was
because when there's a famine, it's usually there's not enough rain and
you're usually fasting and the idea of wearing sackcloth when you fast.
Anyway,
לזו ולזו, lezo ulezo, if it's reddish and sack-like or like the
color of a sack, חרב וחצי רעב באין לעולם, cherev vechizei raav
ba-in laolam, then both things are going to happen. לקה בכניסתו, laka
bechnisato, if the luminary gets these sort of or the sun, let's
say, is when it is going going in, which means setting,
then פורענות שוהה לבוא. puranut shoah lavo. That means that it's the
afflictions are going to come, are going to take time coming, they're
not going to come right away, because this eclipse only occurred towards
the end of the day. ביציאתו, beyetziato, when the sun is coming
out in the beginning of the day, ממהרת לבוא, memaheret lavo, that
means that the bad things are going to happen at the beginning
of the day quickly, the same way this this eclipse happened at
the beginning right at the beginning. Imminent. ויש אומרים חילופא דדברא. veyesh
omrim chilufa dedavara. Some say it's the reverse. That if it goes
towards the end, then it means like you know things happen at
the end because it's like how does רש"י Rashi say the reverse?
If it goes when it's setting, then it'll be fast, oh, because
because it was like no time from from the time that the
eclipse occurred to שכשם שאין לו שהות לשמש ביום, shekeshem sheein lo
shahut leshamesh bayom, like it occurred at a time when there was
no time left. It occurred at a time when the sun was
about to set, when there was no time left. As opposed to
occurring at the beginning when there's plenty of time, suggests more of
an idea of plenty of time. All right, fine. ואין לך כל
אומה ואומה שלוקה שאין אלוהיה לוקה עמה. veein lecha kol uma vauma
sheloka sheein eloheiha loka ima. You have no nation that's that's plagued,
you know, that's beset with troublings or afflictions that's afflicted that the
gods or lowercase g, you know,
the deities that sort of oversee them are not also
afflicted. שנאמר ובכל אלוהי מצרים אעשה שפטים. shenemar uvchol elohei mitzrayim eeseh
shefatim. With all the gods of Egypt I will do judgment. So
this is the idea that there are actually some types of like,
you know, angels or lesser forces that control the doings below and
they also are afflicted at these times. ובזמן שישראל עושים רצונו של
מקום, uvizman sheyisrael osim retzono shel makom, now when the Jewish people
do God's will, אין מתיראים מכל אלו, ein mityarem mikol elu, then
they're they don't have to worry about all these bad signs. None
of these signs afflict them. Right? It's like the idea the גמרא
Gemara says sometimes אין מזל לישראל ein mazal leyisrael or the famous
מדרש Midrash when God says to אברהם, Avraham, you know, ויוצא אותו
החוצה. vayotze oto hachutza.
אברהם Avraham says I looked in the stars and I see that
I won't have you know any children. And God says God took
him outside, which means he took him outside of the realm and
the influence of the stars, lifted him above that influence, you know.
So yes, if you are not doing God's will then you're under
these types of natural influences. And the stars which are seen as
sort of connected to these you know lesser deities and
you're affected by all of those forces, but once you connect to
God then you sort of transcend the natural world and these natural
you know or natural-metaphysical as חז"ל chazal understood sort of forces
and none of this affects you. Okay? שנאמר, shenemar, as the verse
says, כה אמר ה' אל דרך הגויים אל תלמדו. koh amar Hashem
el derech hagoyim al tilmadu. This is what God says, do not
learn from the ways of the nations, which means don't follow in
their deeds. ומאותות השמים אל תחתו, umeotot hashamayim al tichatu, and if
you separate yourself from the nations and don't follow in the deeds,
you'll have nothing to fear from the signs of heaven. כי יחתו
הגויים מהמה. ki yeichatu hagoyim mehema. Let the other nations worry about
them, you won't have to worry about them if you are doing
God's will. עובדי כוכבים יחתו ואין ישראל יחתו. ovdei chochavim yeichatu veein
yisrael yeichatu. It's something for the non-Jews to worry about, not for
the Jews. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Yes, very closely. Well,
okay, if it's not quick we'll talk about it later. I'm sure
you have a very significant important insight, but we're trying to finish
the דף. daf. So you can get with us after. תנו רבנן.
tanu rabanan. Okay. בשביל ארבעה דברים חמה לוקה. bishvil arbaah devarim chamah
loka. For four things the moon is afflicted, especially if we're talking
about it relates to the sins of ישראל, Israel, but which things?
So רש"י Rashi says he doesn't exactly get why the following sins
are matched up with the various things we're going to say,
but let's go ahead and read it. For four things,
I'm sorry, so for four things the sun, I'm sorry, I said
the moon. We'll get to the moon in a minute. For four
things the sun, which is for the non-Jews, is smit. But now
we're going to interpret the meaning not limited to the non-Jews. So
let's take a look. על אב בית דין שמת ואינו נספד כהלכה.
al av beit din shemet veeino nispad kahalacha. The head of of
the בית דין, beit din, the head of like the judiciary dies
and he's not properly mourned. So people don't appreciate the importance of
a legal system
and having a working legal system. ועל נערה מאורסה שצעקה בעיר ואין
מושיע לה, veal naara meorasa shetzaka lair veein moshia lah, like the
verse in the תורה, Torah, a betrothed maiden that is being raped
and nobody came to help her, so the people aren't standing up
for justice. ועל משכב זכור, veal mishkav zachor, on male homosexuality, ועל
שני אחים שנשפך דמם כאחד, veal shenei achim shenishpach damam keechad, and
two brothers who were slaughtered at the same time. So again, exactly,
you know, the first two were connected to the judicial system, the
last two I don't get what, you know, or whatever justice. The
last one whatever.
I don't exactly, bad for the non-Jews.
Yes, bad for the non-Jews too. Look, some of these, most of
these you can somehow connect to the sense of a you know
having a sense of a justice that people, you know, and but
again why the גמרא gemara connects that to homosexuality. I don't exactly...
Well, it's bad for the non-Jews. Yes, it's bad for the non-Jews
too. Look, some of these, most of these you can somehow connect
to the sense of having a sense of justice that people and
but again why the גמרא Gemara connects that to homosexuality I don't
know. ובשביל ארבעה דברים המאורות לוקין U'vshvil arba devarim ha'me'orot lokin for
four reasons the luminaries, which means primarily the moon and the stars
which relates to Jews, are have these things happen to them. על
כותבי פלסתר, al kotvei plaster, people that write falsehood, רש"י Rashi says
it either means like false documents or it means like libel, so
maybe we'll translate it as people that write blogs or... so...
ועל מעידי עדות שקר v'al me'idei edut sheker on people give false
testimony, so again there's a theme here. ועל מגדלי בהמה דקה בארץ
ישראל v'al megadlei behema daka b'Eretz Yisrael those that raise, raising animals
in Israel because it destroys the
vegetation. How that's connected to the others I don't know. ועל קוצצי
אילנות טובות, v'al kotzei ilanot tovot, people that cut down good trees
and רש"י Rashi says even if they're your trees because you are
destroying the beauty of the world that God has given you, and
again how these various pieces are connected,
there's you know maybe there's all there's a sense of lying, betrayal,
but it's not it's hard to put them together and to say
why specifically these even if there is some connecting theme. Okay, just
one more, בשביל ארבעה דברים נכסי בעלי בתים נמסרין למלכות bishvil arba
devarim nichsei ba'alei batim nimsarin la'malchut
for four reasons the property of homeowners, but it means of wealthy
people are seized by the government. על משהי שטרות פרועים, al mash'ei
shetarot pru'im,
people that hold on to promissory notes that have been paid off
because maybe they want to collect twice with it, or maybe they
want to use it as leverage in a court case even if
they're not really, that's what the מהרש"א Maharsha says, even if they're
not planning on actually literally stealing. ועל מלוי ברבית, v'al malvei b'ribit,
people that lend with רבית, ribit, you know, with interest, so basically
here are wealthy people, but of course wealthy people didn't get wealthy
by you know out of you know sort of out of thin
air. So some, I mean obviously some people do it in a
very honest way, but sometimes here are wealthy people that the sins
are the you know the desire for amassing more and more wealth
and the transgressions associated with it. ועל שהיה ספיקה בידם למחות ולא
מיחו, v'al she'haya sfeika b'yadam limchot v'lo michu, and here's again not
similar to the first two points. If you're a wealthy person, then
people will more listen to you. If you know you have a
position of authority, and so if you had the ability to speak
up against certain wrong things that were being done and add your
voice of protest and you did not, then that's also a terrible
failure. ועל שפוסקים צדקה ברבים ואינם נותנים, v'al she'poskim tzadaka b'rabim v'einam
notnim, and they make big pledges of donations and then they don't
satisfy their pledge. So three of the four sort of fit more
with a consistent theme, but the first two is like really about
like unethical business dealings and the last two is more about their
sort of public role. אמר רב בשביל ארבעה דברים נכסי בעלי בתים
יוצאין לטמיון Amar Rav bishvil arba devarim nichsei ba'alei batim yotzin l'timyon
for four reasons the property of homeowners, again wealthy people, gets not
just seized by the government but actually like you know sinks into
the depths, like just somehow gets squandered and lost, like it all
got lost in the stock market. Like technically speaking if you lost,
somebody else gained, but it feels like the money just disappeared. Okay.
על כובשי שכר שכיר, al kovshei s'char sachir, and again we're going
to improper business dealings, they hold back the money that's going to
their hired, hired helpers. ועל עושקי שכר שכיר, v'al oshkei s'char sachir,
those that עושק oshek is a greater degree, right? One is delay,
one is completely not giving them their money, denying them their funds,
money. ועל שפורקין עול מעל צואריהם ונותנין על
חבריהם, v'al she'porkin ol me'al tzavareihem v'notnim al chavareihem, anytime they have
any responsibilities, financial or other, they find a way to get out
of it and to have other people you know assume their responsibilities.
ועל גסות הרוח v'al gasut ha'ruach
and out of haughtiness. וגסות הרוח כנגד כולם, v'gasut ha'ruach k'neged kulam,
and that's bigger than all of them. The מהרש"א Maharsha says it
doesn't just mean bigger than all of them in a straight way
of weighing it, but he actually says that that probably is what
caused all the other sins that we've been talking about, you know.
Is it vulgarity or arrogance? Arrogance.
Arrogance. And he says you know that sense, oh I'm wealthy, I
can do whatever I want, you know that maybe you know is
what also caused, according to the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it, might have
underlined a lot of the other problems as well. אבל בענוים כתיב,
Aval ba'anavim ktiv, but when it comes to humble people it says
וענוים ירשו ארץ והתענגו על רב שלום, v'anavim yirshu aretz v'hit'angu al
rov shalom,
the humble, the meek shall inherit the earth. Look at that, it's
a פסוק pasuk in תהלים, Tehillim, and they will and that's what
it is, the meek shall inherit the earth, and they will and
they will get עונג, oneg, they will get pleasure on the greatness
of peace. So they in the end, if people you're trying to
seize all this stuff for yourself, it's gonna actually and you transgress
and you do unethical things, you'll lose it. But if you act
properly in the end you will reap your reward. הדרן עלך היה
ישן, Hadran alach haya yashen, we're still gonna go begin the next
פרק, perek, but yes, one or two quick questions, yes.
We're in trouble. There's going to be a total lunar eclipse this
פסח, Pesach, this סוכות, Sukkot, next פסח Pesach and next סוכות. Sukkot.
Really? Oh my god. Total lunar eclipse four
four times in the next
two years on the חגים chagim in a row, which is a
very rare occurrence. Okay, יום טוב. Yom Tov. Have a have a
good one.
Ah, so that's nice, tying it back to the rain scene, the
false testimony. Good. Okay, let's start the next פרק. perek. Okay, now
we had two full פרקים prakim on סוכה, sukkah, now we have
one פרק, perek, the third פרק perek devoted fully to the issue
of לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog and then the fourth and the
fifth somewhat continue that theme, somewhat move on to others. So, the
same way this first פרק perek began with all of the, you
know, physical qualities of the סוכה sukkah that make it a כשר
kosher object and don't start with the מצוה mitzvah to sit in
the סוכה, sukkah, so then here too we don't start with the
מצוה mitzvah to take the לולב lulav and אתרוג, esrog, we start
with the physical qualities of the לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog that
make it כשר kosher or otherwise. So, לולב הגזול והיבש פסול, lulav
hagazul vehayavesh pasul, a stolen לולב lulav or a dried up לולב
lulav is invalid. של אשרה ושל עיר הנדחת, shel asherah veshel ir
hanidachat, if it's of an אשרה, asherah, a tree that was worshipped,
or if it's of a city that was to be condemned, the
whole city worshipped עבודה זרה avodah zarah and you're going to kill
the people of the city and you're going to burn down the
city, פסול, pasul, it's invalid. נקטם ראשו, niktam rosho, נפרצו עליו, nifretzu
alav, if the head is cut off or if the leaves are
spread. What does spread mean? רש"י Rashi says it literally means the
leaves are pulled off from the spine and reconnected with like a
rubber band. רש"י Rashi doesn't say rubber band. תוספות Tosafos says it
means that all the leaves are split. So they're still connected, but
they're all split open. Right? You know how a לולב lulav is
like a double leaf, right? That combined? They're all split open. That's
פסול pasul invalid. נפרדו עליו, nifredu alav, if they're somewhat, you know,
fanning out from the center. The leaf itself is not split, it's
not removed from the spine, but it's fanning out. Like people have
seen that, right? Have you seen sometimes those like, you know, those
לולב lulav branches that, you know, that become, you know, like very
wide fan if you leave them alone, the pine, not pine, I
keep saying pine, the palm branches? So that כשר. kasher. Actually, that's
כשר, kasher, everything is connected, it's not even if it's fanning out,
it's okay. רבי יהודה אומר יאגדנו מלמעלה. Rabi Yehudah omer yagdenu milmalah.
רבי יהודה Rabi Yehudah says no, what you should then do is
flatten it out to the spine and bind it up so that
it looks more, you know, whole and looks
better. Now, ציני הר הברזל כשירה, tzinai har habarzel kesherah, if it's
ones that grow on the iron mountain, they're כשרה. kesherah. We'll see
what that means, that they have very short leaves. And finally, so
that's the one thing that's כשר. kasher. Anyway, לולב שיש בו שלשה
טפחים כדי לנענע בו כשר, lulav sheyesh bo shloshah tefachim kedei lenane'a
bo kasher, if the לולב lulav has three טפחים tefachim so you
can shake it, it's כשר. kasher. Why it says "so you can
shake it," the גמרא Gemara is going to actually interpret this to
mean three טפחים tefachim plus an extra טפח tefach to shake it
and make it translated as four טפחים. tefachim. But here you have
a list of invalidities. Now the question is, what makes them invalid?
So some of them, which is like if it's worshipped or if
it's in a city that's going to be destroyed, has this עבודה
זרה avodah zarah connection, that is a principle we'll see that if
you're supposed to destroy it and burn it, it's like it already
doesn't exist, or if it's like, you know, or you know, and
therefore, you know, it doesn't have the right שיעור, shiur, it's completely
standing to be destroyed, that disqualifies it. Fine. But how about these
other things? Why is a dried up לולב lulav invalid? Why is
a stolen? We'll talk about that in a minute. But why is
a dried up לולב lulav invalid? Why with the cut head? What
are these invalidities based on? And if you take a look, very
important debate of רש"י Rashi תוספות, Tosafos, רש"י Rashi says יבש, yavesh,
right? People see it, the third רש"י, Rashi, דבעינן מצוה מהודרת, deba'inan
mitzvah mehuderet,
you need a beautiful מצוה, mitzvah, דכתיב ואנוהו. dikesiv ve'anveihu. This is
my God and I will glorify him, you make מצות mitzvos beautiful.
Now תוספות Tosafos says, what are you talking about? Normally the principle
of נוי מצוה, noy mitzvah, making a beautiful מצוה, mitzvah, if you
don't make the מצוה mitzvah beautiful, you still fulfill the obligation. Why
would that invalidate? And what תוספות Tosafos says, and probably רש"י Rashi
doesn't disagree, is that yes, the reason here the aesthetic appearance
is important for it to be יוצא yotze is because the verse
says פרי עץ הדר, peri eitz hadar, a beautiful, you know, fruit
of the tree or tree of a fruit of a beautiful tree,
but the word הדר, hadar, beautiful, like and notice the word
רש"י Rashi uses, דבעינן מצוה מהודרת, be'inan mitzvah mehuderet, right? He's borrowing
on the word הדר hadar of the verse, so רש"י Rashi probably
doesn't disagree with תוספות. Tosafos. Okay, but רש"י Rashi says what the
word הדר hadar is telling you is that the objects of the
לולב lulav and the ארבע מינים arba minim have to be beautiful.
זה קלי ואנוהו zeh keili ve'anveihu maybe normally isn't a problem, but
here it is, they have to be beautiful. And תוספות, Tosafos, so
רש"י Rashi is using the language, not just the fruit, all of
the ארבע מינים. arba minim. So רש"י Rashi is using the language,
the more general language of זה קלי ואנוהו, zeh keili ve'anveihu, תוספות
Tosafos prefers to just call it הדר. hadar. There's a problem of
הדר, hadar, that idea of beautiful, which is interpreted to not be
limited to the אתרוג, esrog, and that's what demands these aesthetic things
that they look nice. How exactly it's translated, how much does it
get to a point where it's considered not הדר, hadar, that was
up to the rabbis to decide, but the underlying principle is the
idea of הדר. hadar. Let's take a look now at the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, קפסיק ותני kapaska vetani says גמרא, Gemara, it says it
in this sort of categorical way without making any distinctions, לא שנא
ביום טוב ראשון ולא שנא ביום טוב שני. lo shna b'yom tov
rishon velo shna b'yom tov sheni. When we say it's invalid, it
seems to not be distinguishing between the first day יום טוב Yom
Tov and the second day יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now, second day
יום טוב Yom Tov could mean if you translate it literally, narrowly,
the גלות galus second day יום טוב. Yom Tov. But it's more
generally understood by the ראשונים Rishonim to be referring to the idea
of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. That not... is there different criteria for
first day יום טוב Yom Tov and second day יום טוב? Yom
Tov? We tend to assume no, second day is patterned after first
day. So they assume what the גמרא's Gemara focusing on rather is
the question of חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Do we have the same
invalidities on חול המועד Chol HaMoed for the ארבע מינים Arba Minim
that we have on the first day? Why should it be different?
Because you'll remember that the first day is the biblical מצווה. mitzvah.
ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון. u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon.
The only reason we take it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed is
to remember what they did in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but
it's only rabbinic. So are we going to apply the same problems
on the first day that we apply on the חול המועד Chol
HaMoed that we applied on the first day? So the גמרא Gemara
says, the משנה Mishna is not distinguishing. It seems like it's the
same issue. So בשלמא, bishlama, so it
says בשלמא יבש, bishlama yavesh, I get why if it's dried up,
that's not be good on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, הדר בעינן וליכא.
hadar beinan velika. Again, here's a גמרא Gemara exactly uses the word
הדר. hadar. Beautiful, based on the verse. That's what you need, right?
And there clearly should be a requirement on all of the days.
Okay. The idea of הדר, hadar, that should be a requirement even
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. אלא גזול, ela gazul, but stolen, why
is that a problem? בשלמא יום טוב ראשון, bishlama Yom Tov Rishon,
I get the first day, כתיב לכם, ksiv lachem, you shall take
for you, משלכם, mishelachem, you have to own it. אלא ביום טוב
שני אמאי לא? ela beyom tov sheni amai lo? What's the problem?
Because we know you can borrow a לולב lulav on חול המועד,
Chol HaMoed, so why can't you have a stolen לולב lulav on
חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? What is the problem of
stolen if we know that we don't insist on ownership during the
חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? We only insist that you own it on
the first day. Okay, so we will pick up with this, leave
this question hanging, and pick up with that tomorrow. Okay.
You see that earlier piece of the סוגיא, sugya, would you say
there's an implicit acknowledgment, I mean even in the תנ"ך, Tanakh, an
acknowledgment of other of a
pantheon of other gods for other people? Is there an implicit recognition
that what's truly at the heart of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is
disloyalty? It's not, it's less about truth.
That is the question, you know, that's the whole... hello, hon.
Hello,
what's going on?
What?
You have a good day. Thank you. Use the one near the
refrigerator. Use
the one near the refrigerator. Name of him,
אברהם. Avraham. Wonderful. All right,
are
you
okay?
Are you safe? Too
loud?
You all have a good day. See you later. Thank you.